<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Life of Herod the Great wherein his inhumane cruelties are briefly but accurately related, with an account of his fatal and miserable end.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48417</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15699648</idno>
  <idno type="VID">104450</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248523369</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36473</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">15699648</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1152:45)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Life of Herod the Great wherein his inhumane cruelties are briefly but accurately related, with an account of his fatal and miserable end.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 [i.e. 40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Enoch Wyer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXVIII [1678]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, Aug. 6, 1677. R. L'estrange."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Herod --  I, --  King of Judea, 73-4 B.C.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104450:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE OF Herod the Great.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN His Inhumane Cruelties are Briefly but Accurately related. With an account of his fatal and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable End.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licensed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Aug.</hi> 6. 1677.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>R. L'estrange.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>Enoch Wyer,</hi> at the <hi>White Hart</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, MDCLXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:104450:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE following Discourse gives thee a brief but plain account of the Life and Death of the cruel <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> whose savage and blood-thirsty na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could not be tamed by the most en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing arguments of Relation and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; he being prompted partly by vain fears, and partly by groundless Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, to commit those horrid cruelties, scarce ever parallel'd (sure never exceeded) by any Age.</p>
            <p>And although Heaven (which is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times slow in <hi>executing sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="tcp:104450:3"/> evil-doers</hi>) did suffer him for a while to pass unpunished, yet at length the just judgment of an offended God did legibly appear in the strange and misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble end of this cruel Tyrant; all which (that I may not longer detain thee) thou wilt find more fully discovered in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Discourse.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104450:3"/>
            <head>The Life of HEROD.</head>
            <p>SOme fifty years before the Birth of Christ, <hi>Hirca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> (a good man, but bad King) reign'd over <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> by permission of the <hi>Romans:</hi> he us'd as much remisness in his charge, as he practis'd innocence in manners; his over-much easiness bringing him to a kind of stupidity. Being made sensible of his own weakness, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd the dignity and burden of Government to his Brother <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> a courageous but unsuccessful man in all his enterprizes.</p>
            <p>These changes, and the dependance this Royalty had under the <hi>Roman</hi> power, gave occasion to many to court this Government; amongst whom <hi>Antipater,</hi> the Father of <hi>Herod,</hi> an <hi>Idumean</hi> by Nation, a wealthy and most sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til man, and able to bring to pass great matters, had of a long time a plot upon the Kingdom of <hi>Judea;</hi> and well-seeing, that whilst the courageous and prudent <hi>Aristobu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> bore sway, his design would be but vain, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to dismount him, and seat <hi>Hircanus</hi> again upon the Throne. First, by his cunning insinuations to the people holding forth the easie and gentle disposition of <hi>Hircanus,</hi> whose yeilding up his right, was doubtless the unparallel'd emblem of pure modesty; That the more unworthy he esteem'd himself to rule, the more was his worth; That the glory he so easily sought to decline in his own person, would wait upon him to his Tomb; and that the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and facility of his nature, was far more sutable to the piety and humour of the <hi>Jews,</hi> than the lofty and turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104450:4"/> spirit of <hi>Aristobulus;</hi> that they had forsaken a King blame-worthy in nothing, but in surplusage of goodness; and had subjugated themselves to the cruel austerity of one, whose ill managery would quickly make them feel the ruine of all <hi>Palestine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These subtil remonstrances quickly found credulity enough in the minds of the people, at that time curst with a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious desire of Innovation; so that now having only <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> to ply, towards him he payeth all respect and testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of amity, which being no hard matter, in a very short time he becometh sole Tutor and Master of his flexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble spirit. And now the actions of <hi>Hircanus</hi> sought no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther issue but the guidance of <hi>Antipater;</hi> and to farther his taking up of Arms against his Brother, for re posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing himself, upon the Throne he causeth not daily to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to him, that this giving away his power to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was inconsistent with his honour and life, rendring him lamentably despicable; whilst it rais'd his Brother to a superabundance in pomp; that a Kingdom was a Shirt never to be put off but with life; that the life he led was good for a religious person, but not for a King; and in fine, that the people most passionately desired to see him re-established in the Throne of his Ancestors.</p>
            <p>With this and such like discourses <hi>Hircanus</hi> is moved to give <hi>Antipater</hi> commission to make war or peace as best pleased him, which he instantly goeth about, with no small success.</p>
            <p>In these commotions, the <hi>Romans</hi> (then powerful over all) find themselves concern'd, so that <hi>Pompey</hi> having then under his Conduct a terrible Army in <hi>Syria,</hi> becometh Umpire, and is applied unto by the two Brothers, who both well perceived the main of the business to hang upon the favour of the <hi>Romans.</hi> At first <hi>Aristobulus</hi> seemed to have most favour, as the person from whom the <hi>Romans</hi> had greatest cause to hope the readiest service for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, had not <hi>Antipater</hi> raised most injurious aspersions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104450:4"/> upon him, daily to disgrace him, and draw the <hi>Romans</hi> to a distrust of his spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aristobulus</hi> perceiving now this subtile pernicious man to abuse the name and weakness of his Brother, and that he design'd nothing less than to sell them both to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> resolv'd with more animosity than force to resist this shock; but shrinking under the burden of his enterprize, is taken, put in fetters, and carried in <hi>Pompey's</hi> Triumph to <hi>Rome;</hi> whilst <hi>Jerusalem</hi> is made tributary, the place of High-Priest given to <hi>Hircanus,</hi> and all authority in the hands of <hi>Antipater,</hi> which he still managed to the lessen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hircanus</hi> dignity; and becoming aged, he makes his eldest Son <hi>Phaselus</hi> Governour of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and giveth to <hi>Herod</hi> the Tetrarchy of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and shortly after died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> nothing inferiour to his Father in policy, prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting his plots and examples, inseparably united himself to the <hi>Romans,</hi> gaining them with all manner of services, and entertaining <hi>Hircanus,</hi> to serve his turn as a shadow, with all manner of complacent flattery; whilst the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Judea</hi> as yet is so far from him, that his elder Brother <hi>Phaselus</hi> held the best part, and <hi>Alexander</hi> second Son to <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> and the unfortunate Successor to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers unhappiness, putting himself in the field with all the Troops he could amass. <hi>Aristobulus</hi> and his Son <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> escaping captivity in <hi>Rome,</hi> prevail with the <hi>Parthians</hi> for assistance, and so handle the matter, by force and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, that they stir up <hi>Hircanus</hi> and <hi>Phaselus</hi> to be on their side, hereby giving <hi>Herod</hi> matter enough to work upon, until <hi>Alexander</hi> was overcome and killed by the help of the <hi>Romans Hircanus</hi> unworthily and cruelly used by his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>Antigonus,</hi> by whose command both his ears were cut off, and so necessarily fell into that irregularity for which the <hi>Jewish</hi> Law discharges any to officiate in the High-Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. <hi>Phaselus</hi> enraged at the turn of fortune, knocketh out his own brains against a rock, flying the fury of his Brother <hi>Herod,</hi> who ceased not to pursue miserable <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonus,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104450:5"/> who is afterwards taken and imprisoned, and by the command of <hi>M. Antony</hi> beheaded at <hi>Antioch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold <hi>Herod</hi> now mounted to the top of the wheel, having none to grapple with for the Kingdom of <hi>Judea,</hi> but aged <hi>Hircanus, Alexandra</hi> his only Daughter, and <hi>Aristobulus</hi> and <hi>Mariamne,</hi> her Children by <hi>Alexander</hi> second Son to the former <hi>Aristobulus;</hi> these being the last remainder of the ancient and noble <hi>Asmodean</hi> Race, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Herod</hi> still to seek after the most sure ways of esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing that Government in his own person. He cunningly insinuateth with <hi>Hircanus,</hi> by the frequent demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of amity, and prevailing with <hi>Alexandra,</hi> tho a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man far differing from her Fathers temper, and of a haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty spirit, is married to <hi>Mariamne</hi> the most beautiful Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess in the earth. Never were beauty and virtue so disgrac'd in any match, she to whom the Princes of the world would have joyed to pay homage, and all obsequious service at her feet, is now beheld the wife of cruel <hi>Herod,</hi> who had nothing humane in him but lineament and shape; thus matching the Lamb with the Wolf, and the Dove with the Faulcon, by the passionate endeavours of <hi>Herod,</hi> and the haughty designs of <hi>Alexandra,</hi> to have her succession to govern; much mistaking the disposition of <hi>Herod,</hi> who practising quite contrary to the expectation of <hi>Alexandra</hi> and <hi>Mariamne</hi> his Wife, and perceiving the young <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus</hi> a most accomplished Prince, to whom every one desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Miter in place of <hi>Hircanus,</hi> now incapacitated of the High Priesthood, which he fear'd might some day turn him out of all the Government, introduceth a stranger <hi>Jew</hi> named <hi>Ananel,</hi> and createth him High-Priest; thus shaking off <hi>Aristobulus</hi> from an honour to which Blood, Nature, and the consent of the whole world had called him. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra</hi> is forced to dissemble the rage this bred in her, till <hi>Mariamne,</hi> in the calmness of her noble spirit, should use some opportune endeavor with the King, to whom not long after, finding him in a pleasant humour, she declared in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104450:5"/> her natural sweetness, That he was the support of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Family, that for her self she only desired to breath her last with honour, That if he would be pleased to bestow the Myter to her Brother <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> it were to make a creature, from whom he had no cause at all to fear, his Throne being throughly established, and having the tender youth of this Prince as a piece of soft wax in his hands; That this act would make him rule in the hearts of the <hi>Jews</hi> as well as in <hi>Provinces,</hi> and that the honour which she had by matching with him, seemed not compleat to her, whilst she saw her most near Relations kept from Degrees, wherein he might establish them without prejudice of his Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> by the pleasant charmings of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> suffered himself to be gained, and having deliberated the affair, he resolved to give the High-Priesthood to young <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> not without discovering to <hi>Alexandra</hi> the resentment he had of her behaviour, giving her to know that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood very well the mutinous and turbulent contrivances her spirit laboured in, endeavouring to embroil and confound all affairs, seeking to take a Scepter from him, whom Heaven had assisted in purchasing it with so much travel and pain, to put it in the hands of an Infant, to the prejudice of the Queen her Daughter; all which injuries he now willingly forgave and forgot, and was now to confirm her Son in the Priesthood as he had ever designed, and that <hi>Ananels</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stallment was only during the time that <hi>Aristobulus</hi> should come to maturity. <hi>Alexandra</hi> at this was wonderfully overjoyed, declaring, that the Priesthood was all she aimed at, for her Son being only desirous to keep the Myter in the Royal Family: as for the Kingdom she never had any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tension unto it, being very well satisfied to dye, leaving her Son High-priest, and her Daughter Queen; that if she had exceeded in words, she was excusable as a passionate Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to her Son; that as Mother-in-Law to the King some more than ordinary freedom might be allowed her; and now
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104450:6"/> the Kings discretion having accomplished all her expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there was nothing should hinder her from living in the most dutiful manner imaginable.</p>
            <p>The Feast of Tabernacles being come, <hi>Ananel</hi> is depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and <hi>Aristobulus</hi> beginneth to exercise his office, to the most wonderful satisfaction of all the Jewish Nation. He was of a gallant stature, tall and streight, and at that time se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen years of age. When the people beheld him clothed with the Pontifical Garments, which he replenished to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with Majesty, and going towards the Altar to perform those Ceremonial Rites as are proper at that Feast; their hearts were raised up above imagination, their hopes bloom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed afresh to see this branch of the <hi>Macabean</hi> race. Her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions were haughty on his behalf, and inlarged so far in his applause, both in words and behaviour, that <hi>Herod</hi> now begun to blame his credulity, and suffering himself to be possest with a furious jealousie, he causeth the High-Priest, his Mother and the Queen to be so narrowly watched, that they moved not, nor conversed any where but he was advertised of it. The modest <hi>Mariamne</hi> amongst those sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions lived in grace, sweetning these acerbities with a most wonderful discretion. But <hi>Alexandra,</hi> who never could endure restraint, and who above all things delighted in Royal Liberty, choosing rather to expose her self to the cruelty of <hi>Herods</hi> sword, than ly inchain'd to his will, well knowing the famous <hi>Cleopatra</hi> now residing in her domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> bore a most malitious prejudice towards <hi>Herod,</hi> for that he endeavoured to alienate the heart of <hi>Mark Antony</hi> from her; she writes a Letter to <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating therein, that the many comfortless calamities, tho the Daughter and Mother of a King, <hi>Herods</hi> cruelty had brought upon her, occasioned her to beg the protection and security of the life of her and her Son, since God had blest her with accomplishments and greatness sufficient to be a Sanctuary for the Innocent, and an Altar for the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed; that she lived continually amongst spies, in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104450:6"/> black apprehensions of Death; that her sufferings were num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berless; that her shelter was only what could be comforting to them, till the storm were blown over, which she earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreated of her, whereby Queen <hi>Cleopatra</hi> should declare her infinite magnificence, and oblige them to a perpetual gratitude. <hi>Cleopatra</hi> having received these Letters, made a ready answer, inviting her and her Son to hasten to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and protesting she should esteem it an inspeakable glory to serve as a Sanctuary and refuge for such an afflicted Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess.</p>
            <p>Resolutions of departure are taken, without imparting the purpose to <hi>Mariamne:</hi> she causeth two Coffins to be made (such as are used to carry dead persons to their place of Burial, a bad presage) to put her self and Son into, hereby to elude the watchfulness of the Guards, and so to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Sea-side, where a Ship attended her, by this means to save her life under the shadow of death. But by ill hap this design is discovered to one <hi>Sabbion,</hi> who faileth not to reveal all to <hi>Herod,</hi> so that by his order the poor Lady and her Son are surprised in the Coffins and taken out of the Sepulcher of the dead to return to the living, amongst whom she could not expect to remain long. <hi>Herod</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, whether he feared <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> or would not wholly affright <hi>Alexandra,</hi> contain'd himself in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary course of dissimulation, without speaking one upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing word, so that she begun to believe that he had buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all in oblivion. When one day at Dinner <hi>Herod</hi> being desirous to go afterwards to some exercise, <hi>Aristobulus</hi> accompanieth him, and thereafter by some of <hi>Herods</hi> emis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, being perswaded to go a Bathing, whilst he poor Lamb, skipped up and down, not knowing the unhappiness attended him, they smother the most comly <hi>Aristobulus</hi> in the waters, as if his own unskilfulness had occasioned his death. Behold now the glory of the Royal house of <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modan,</hi> smothered under waters in an age, in a beauty, in an innocency which made this accident as lamentable as uncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104450:7"/>
            <p>This news amazed the whole City of Jerusalem, and all the adjacent parts of <hi>India,</hi> to find themselves depriv'd of so glorious a High Priest, in the first year of his office, and eighteenth year of his age: in every place there was nothing to be seen or heard, but tears, groans, horror, astonishment, and the fear of death: You would have said that every fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily did bear their first-born to burial, as it was once in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Above all, disconsolate <hi>Alexandra</hi> afflicted her self with incurable sorrow, using behaviour and expression so full of lamentation and grief, that never any thing exceeded the real disturbances of spirit she thereby exprest, whilst the pious <hi>Mariamne</hi> imployed her admirable patience to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the impetuous violences of an incurable sorrow; and and breaking through the dampest confusion that this most lamentable accident had cast her int, she turns her self to her God, with affectionate heart expressing, that since the life of her hopes, and the stay of her family was now taken away by a secret Judgment of his providence, ever to be adored, but not searched after, she begged grace from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that from the many acerbities that waited for her, she might comfortably search out such sweetnesses, as usually Gods true Children do, and receive them as the assurances of future happiness; and here being stopt with tears, she remained the most sorrowfull Creature in the World. In this sad comfort <hi>Herod</hi> faileth not to act his part, never any appeared more sorrowful than he; he detesteth play, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuseth fortune, and complaineth that Heaven had rob'd him of that subject on whom he resolved to demonstrate the love and respect he bore to the royal blood; and most cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniously goeth to visit the comfortless Mother and Sister of the smothered <hi>Aristobolus,</hi> who sate weeping over the dead body, where the tears gushed from his eyes with such appearance of sincerity and sorrow, that one would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved him altogether innocent; and after he had born a fair share of weeping (which his dissembling nature could easily effect) with the comfortless Ladies, he endeavoured
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104450:7"/> to asswage their excessive sorrow, and remove the jealousie they might have of him, telling them that he came not so suddenly to wipe away their tears, having enough to do to command his own, which had but too much cause to be shed; but that time could only now plaister up their sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; that he would perform for the memory of the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d whatever could be expected from the most affectionate fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that hereafter he would be a true son to <hi>Alexandra,</hi> a true Husband and brother to <hi>Mariamne,</hi> since God was pleased to redouble those obligations in him by the loss they had suffered, and so retiring as having behaved himself free from all suspition of offence, he caused the funerals of the dead to be celebrated with such pomp and magnificence, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be added thereto; the simple and ignorant, suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed this to be from a real and sincere affection, but the wisest said, they were the tears of the Crocodile, of whom was <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra,</hi> so that joyning the passion of her sorrow to her pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of revenge, she immediately after the obsequies giveth notice to <hi>Cleopa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra</hi> of all that had passed in so mournful a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that every word seemed to be sleeped in tears of blood: <hi>Cleopatra</hi> suddenly taketh fire, and effecteth the affair with that ardour she would her own, in plying <hi>Mark Antony,</hi> who regarding <hi>Herod</hi> as his Creature, would not willingly understand those complaints, but the uncessant importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities <hi>Cleopatra</hi> used, perpetually filled M. <hi>Antonies</hi> eares, crying how unsupportable it was to see a stranger hold a Scepter to which he could pretend no right, to massacre the Heir with such barbarous cruelty▪ and torment with servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude against all equity and reason, all the Royal race, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him, that at length he swore he would send for <hi>Herod</hi> and examine the business, and accordingly <hi>Herod</hi> is summoned to appear at <hi>Laodicea</hi> before <hi>Mark Antony</hi> to purge himself of the Murder of <hi>Aristobolus,</hi> of which he was the supposed Author: This distracted and tore his spirits on all sides, on the one hand assaulted by the image of Death, and the voice of blood, on the other he saw
<pb facs="tcp:104450:8"/> Mr. <hi>Antony,</hi> on whom depended his fortune, wholly guided by the counsel of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> his mortal Enemy; but the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil that most perplexed him was a furious jealousy, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that M. <hi>Antony,</hi> a wanton and lascivious Prince, being possest with the most singular beauty of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> whom he much regarded to enjoy, would make him serve as the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of his fatal love, which moved him to endeavour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, and draw out the business to a greater length: But no excuses prevailing, having set his Mother, and <hi>Salome</hi> his Sister to watch over the deportments of those he thought had wrought him the mischief, he taketh his leave of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra</hi> and <hi>Mariamne</hi> his wife, without any show of amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or discontent, as if he had been going a short journey of pleasure, and after all taking <hi>Joseph</hi> his brother aside, to whom he spoke, declaring that his innocence was now pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully assaulted by the secret malice of some persons of his Court, over which he hoped to triumph by his integrity, as he had already by deeds of Armes over hostility, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otherways his being charged to <hi>Laodicea</hi> behoved to be a meer plot, to shorten his days for the beauty of his Wife, that M. <hi>Antony,</hi> might have more liberty for his unbridled passion, conjuring him by the love he owed to a brother, if perhaps he should be used otherways, then his quality and innocence deserved, instantly to kill <hi>Mariamne,</hi> that his death might not be waited upon with the injury of his bed, by anothers injoying her, that if the souls of the dead have any feeling of the affairs of the World, that might solace him, and so wishing him thereafter to possess himself of the Kingdom, which <hi>Joseph</hi> though very much amazed, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> now setteth forward in his journey, carrying with him the richest of his treasure to make presents, and shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all things as much confidence in his countenance as he hatched dispair in his heart; in a short time he arriveth at <hi>Laodicea,</hi> where he found many strange informations, and and horrid Articles given in against him, holding out, that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104450:8"/> nothing so much perplexed him then to see <hi>Aristobulus</hi> the true heir of the Kingdom alive; that the power he had was but a regency until his maturity; that he had converted his regency to a Tyranny in his own person, keeping off the Royal blood from dignities to advance persons of no worth, witness <hi>Ananel,</hi> that the change he afterwards made was out of no true affection but to prevent popular Commotions which he forsaw would arise upon rejecting the Royal blood; that the applause and alacrity <hi>Aristobulus</hi>'s preferment to the Priesthood did cause in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> had bred in him a restless fury, and desire of exterpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that race so as to force them to seek shelter in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations, and that at length this young Prince was drowned in the Water, not alone by himself, but manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly smothered by the insolent youth of the Houshold, and bosom of <hi>Herod</hi> by his order: The picture of this poor Prince, whose beauty was of singular admiration, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to M. <hi>Antony</hi> to cry for justice, and <hi>Cleopatra</hi> not cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to lay all irons in the fire, removed the battery against <hi>Herod</hi> most forcibly, but in fine, his accusations being read, he who wanted no eloquence, with a modest yet sprightly countenance replyed,</p>
            <p>That he never had any purpose to flatter <hi>Hircanus, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra</hi> or any of that race for the Scepter of <hi>Judea;</hi> that he held that Kingdom of the Illustrious M. <hi>Antony,</hi> in whom his greatness did arise, and in whom his hope centered, that at M. <hi>Antonies</hi> command he was not only willing to leave the Scepter, but his life; that now he found his reputation (more dear to him then his life) persecuted by women, and wondered that the Celestial soul of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> could enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain so much spleen against a King who never failed in any kind of respect; for <hi>Alexandra</hi> he did not admire, since her behaviour was so agreeable to her fierce and haughty spirit wherewith she had ever opposed his patience, that he being the peaceable possessor of that Kingdom by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>Romans,</hi> there was no appearance that either
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104450:9"/> he needed, or would cause or commit so horrible a crime; that the death of <hi>Aristobulus</hi> could not settle his affairs, which were already so firmly established by the authority of the <hi>Romans;</hi> and that notwithstanding he had ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to preserve and prefer the Royal blood to Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; <hi>Hircanus</hi> he tenderly preserved after he had procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his liberty from the <hi>Parthian</hi> Bondage; That he had shared the Crown with <hi>Mariamne;</hi> that he had given the Priesthood to <hi>Aristobulus</hi> of his free good will, and not by constraint; and that it was not sooner given him, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the minority of his Age ran not equal with his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet in effect he was made High-Priest at eighteen years of Age, a favour very extraordinary, that <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> had all freedom imaginable in his Court, except the liberty of ruining her self, if she desired to make a voyage into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> what needed her to hide her self in a Coffin, since one word had been sufficient both for obtaining my consent, and a train agreeable to her quality; what reason or necessity had she to counterfeit a false peril in a real safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and distrust him who made her live in all reposed assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances? That when he discovered this practice, he made it his work rather to appear the spectacle of Patience, then use the least word of bitterness; that <hi>Aristobulus</hi> was now dead, whom he passionately lamented, for he loved him; that he dyed not in his house, but by an unpreventable accident, sporting in that faithless element the water, that he dyed amongst the youth of the Court with whom he daily disported himself; that it was hard to make him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for the youthful levities of <hi>Alexandra's</hi> Son, as if he were his governor, or of the inconstancy of watry ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as if he were Lord over them.</p>
            <p>The pernicious hypocrite spoke to this purpose with so much grace and probability, that he gained many hearts, so that now he waits in <hi>M Antonies</hi> Court, in that dignity which well became the King of <hi>Judea,</hi> expecting his sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Justification; and on all occasions he managed his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104450:9"/> affairs with so much wisdom and liberality, that now <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra's</hi> diligence is looked upon as the passion of a woman ill advised.</p>
            <p>Whilst these things were handled in <hi>M. Antonies</hi> Court, <hi>Alexandra</hi> and <hi>Mariamne</hi> are narrowly eyed by the watchful Mother and Sister of <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Joseph</hi> his uncle, who played the Jaylor, thorow frequent visits began to burn in love, passionately affecting the most incomparable <hi>Mariamne,</hi> this passion rendered him foolish and full of babble, so that one day, whether out of folly or drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, speaking of <hi>Herod,</hi> he told her, that in case he was put to death at <hi>Laodicea,</hi> he had left commandment to kill her, the better to enjoy others company in the other world; at these words the two Princesses were exceedingly astoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. But in the end <hi>Herod</hi> returneth victorious, in which time his Mother and Sister failed not presently to serve him up a dish of their own dressing, and tell him that <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra</hi> had designed to put her self into the power of the <hi>Romans,</hi> by a secret familiarity kept between <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Mariamne;</hi> this was to be effectual. <hi>Herod</hi> who ever was extreamly jealous, gave credit, and taking <hi>Mariamne</hi> aside, challengeth her whence this correspondence with <hi>Joseph</hi> grew, which the chast Queen so modestly vindicated her self of, that the cruel wretch perceiving very well how far her thoughts were alienated from such wickedness, being ashamed of his credulity, he thanked her for her fidelity, asking her pardon, with a thousand protestations of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual affection; the good Lady easily discovering the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie, answered, that certainly his affection behoved to be most sincere, since he desired so much her company in the other world. <hi>Herod</hi> well understood by half a word what she would say, but without seeming concern'd, parting from <hi>Mariamne,</hi> he entered in such a desperate fury, because <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph</hi> had betrayed him, that without tryal or hearing one word for his justification, he causeth him in that instant to be murdered. It was a wonder <hi>Mariamne</hi> was not alike
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104450:10"/> served, but the irrefragable proofs of her innocence and the impatient ardours of his love withheld the stroak. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> he shut up, keeping her apart from the Queen; well judging it was in her shop all the Councels for his ruine were forged and filed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hircanus</hi> the true and lawful King, who first raised <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater,</hi> and afterwards saved <hi>Herods</hi> life: seating him on the throne to the prejudice of his own Relations, had all this while lived in quiet, being eighty years of age, worn with decrepidness, is most barbarously murdered by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of <hi>Herod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who having the news brought him of the death of <hi>M. Antony,</hi> in the Actuack battel against <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi> thereby losing him who lent his shoulders to underprop him on all occasions, thought it most dangerous to leave any remainder of the blood-Royal alive behind him, whilst it behoved him to search out <hi>Caesar,</hi> who was then supposed to be at <hi>Rhodes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The death of <hi>M. Antony</hi> struck him into the very heart, and it was no wonder, seeing his support lost, his affairs which he supposed to be so well established, were in one night dissolved, and that he had him for an enemy, who was now stepping into the Empire of the World. Amidst these fears he resolves to prostrate himself at the feet of the Emperour, and after he had shut up <hi>Alexandra</hi> and <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amne</hi> in a strong Fort, under the custody of <hi>Joseph</hi> the Treasurer, and <hi>Sohemus</hi> the <hi>Iturean,</hi> leaving the charge of the Kingdom to <hi>Pheroras,</hi> he goeth directly to <hi>Rhodes,</hi> leaving the Queen and her Mother, not so much grieving at their own restraint, as the barbarous death of aged <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus;</hi> the guards at first seemed severe in their countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces towards the two Princesses, but as no Iron but it soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the fire, so in the end <hi>Sohemus</hi> visited them so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that he felt the fiery arrows fly from the eyes of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riamne</hi> so sharp that they moved his heart with compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, judging it a hard matter to hold a Queen in Captivity,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104450:10"/> who was able to inthrall all hearts with her many supere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent excellencies; he began to shew her a pleasing coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and after passing several discourses, the Queen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring to him that as he might expect she could not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be unable, so she would never be ungrateful, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him to tell her to what end King <hi>Herod</hi> held them there, and in what condition the affairs of the times were in; <hi>Sohemus</hi> to this made positive resistance, minding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh the vengeance of <hi>Herod</hi> on his Uncles: But in the end the earnest solicitations of the Queen, and the supposition that either <hi>Herod</hi> should not return King, or that <hi>Mariam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> protection might work his reconciliation, touched with compassion, revealed to her that the same Commission was left with him by <hi>Herod</hi> at his going to <hi>Rhodes,</hi> which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he gave his Uncle at his going to <hi>Laodicea;</hi> and that if the exceeding watchfulness of <hi>Pheroras</hi> and his guards did not hinder, he would endeavour to set them at liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> is now safely arrived in <hi>Rhodes,</hi> the sea, wind, men, and all his affairs going successfully, he knew he could not conceal the services he had done for <hi>Mark An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony;</hi> and therefore resolves to cover them with the mantle of vertue; and seeing <hi>Augustus</hi> was a Prince born to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, was just and generous, and endeavoured to make faithful servants in the change of affairs; he deceives him under the shadow of vertue, with the colour of constancy, and pretext of fidelity, and in a most submiss, yet confident manner, he applieth himself to the Emperor, expressing, that his Person and Crown were both at his feet; since the gods had put the Empire of the universe in his hands, it was good reason all should depend on his greatness: he declared that he had been a great friend of <hi>M. Antony,</hi> who was miserably seduced by <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> to take money from him, and councel from her, which destroyed his fortune, to raise up that of <hi>Caesars;</hi> that had he believed him, his ruine had not so soon befallen him, that he had followed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104450:11"/> him to the brink of the grave, and now was able to render him nought but tears, that now to <hi>Caesar</hi> all services were due, which with most sincere heartiness he readily tendered, begging he might be pleased to accept, on condition he should not be inforced to hear or speak evil of his old Master; whom though he could no longer serve, yet for ever would love; <hi>Augustus</hi> was wonderfully taken with this liberty which <hi>Herod</hi> had used in his address, thinking he was made of that metal whereof good servants are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, he confirmeth unto him the Crown, with no other alteration but that he should live peaceably in his territories, and be as faithful to him as he had been to <hi>M. Anto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y;</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this not ceasing to put himself forward in the favour of <hi>Augustus,</hi> he went with him in his voyage to <hi>Egypt,</hi> where he performed many good offices for the Emperor, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus prosperously effected all his business, he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth triumphantly to <hi>Jerusalem</hi> to the great amazement of both his friends and foes.</p>
            <p>So soon as he arrived in this Capital City, being secure of all his affairs; he hastneth to salute the Queen whom already he had caused to be set at liberty, and was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rst gave her the news of his happy success; he was so puffed up with his prosperity, and the love of so amiable an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that he could not detain himself from the excess of vaunting, which <hi>Mariamne</hi> keeping fresh in her memory her restraint she had been in, and the command for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering her, he had left both to <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Sohemus,</hi> she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived all his endearments and flatteries with such indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of behaviour, that <hi>Herod</hi> well perceived she did not at all congratulate his fortune, nor entertain him with that lovely behaviour as became an affectionate wife, which he expounding to be a tryfling melancholy humor, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make it vanish by renewing his flatteries, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining her with all manner of amorous Courtship not usual to his Nature; <hi>Mariamne</hi> on the other hand imployed her self no otherwise then in sending forth most grievous sighs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104450:11"/> and groans; in great discontent he retired, shaking his head in a most passionate anger, and now began to swell in his breast a violent suspition that <hi>Sohemus</hi> had used the like intemperance of tongue which <hi>Joseph</hi> had, which so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded him being torn as it were in pieces on all hands by love, jealousie, anger, and suspition; he became disar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of all humane reason; sometime resolving to brandish his sword in the blood of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> but love proving of more force withheld the stroak; and whilst again he is cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing love for making him merciful, contrary to his disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Cypre</hi> an <hi>Arabian,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Salome</hi> his Sister seeing him so passionate, ceased not to blow up the fire they had been so long in kindling; and as he stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up and down transported with fury and anger, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Sister <hi>Salome</hi> thinking it high time to strike the stroak amongst the many calumnies she had laid upon the Queen, which were all as wicked as ridiculous; having suborned on <hi>Belial</hi> the Kings Cup-bearer, she informeth that <hi>Mariamne</hi> had addressed her self to him, to corrupt him with many promises, that he might give <hi>Herod</hi> a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of dispatch, which he never had yet given ear unto; that if his Majesty pleased to examine the matter, she was confident <hi>Belial</hi> would give the true account thereof, that it was the Queens intention, and that she only required the service of his hands; this wicked fellow is forthwith brought into the Chamber, where in cold blood, he solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly makes oath hereof, which so inflamed the heart of the Tyrant with rage, that causing him to lay hold on the Eunuch the Queen most trusted in, him he caused to be put to the torture, after grievous torments inflicted, they force him to say that he had seen <hi>Sohemus</hi> talking in secret with <hi>Mariamne,</hi> the Eunuch is set at liberty and <hi>Sohemus</hi> put on the rack, but no torment soever being able to make him confess any thing, he is here massacred in the place. The Tyrant persisting in his fury, and drinking in deep draughts of gall and bitterness of his deadly chollar, without giving
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104450:12"/> truce to his spirit, he calls to him those with whom he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted his bloody designs, and sending for the Queen, he there in a long harrangue declareth to them, that he had cherished the whole Family of <hi>Hircanus,</hi> in his bosome in the time of its decay and confusion; that instead of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude he had met with nothing but malice and poyson; that the Queen his wife imitating her Mother, was always rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to disquiet his repose, that having returned from a voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age full of danger, with success of his affairs, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his most serious indearments; yet could not draw from her a pleasant look, or good word; that he would not inlarge, recounting the many ingrateful injuries she had perpetrated upon him; he desires them to give ear to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial</hi> his faithful servant, whom she had endeavoured to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born to give him a Potion on purpose to poison him to death, thereby to make him a sport for the malice, and mark for the treacheries of a woman, whom neither love nor bounty could reclaim; desiring them to resolve what to do, he being unwilling to direct himself herein by his own advice.</p>
            <p>This nose-led Councel well perceiving that his purpose wholly bent upon the ruine of the Queen, without giving her the allowance of answering to vindicate her self, they all agree she suffer death; which sentence the glorious <hi>Amazon</hi> weary of <hi>Herod</hi>'s perverse humour, with a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant but undaunted countenance, denoting innocence, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least impatient frown, or recriminating word, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully heard, being what she long expected; <hi>Herod</hi> however after reflecting on the horridness of the deed, and conscious of the Queens innocence, commanded she should be kept in a Prison in the Palace, with delay of Execution. But the cruel-hearted <hi>Salome,</hi> who had raised the Storm, not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling things should be done by halfs, and <hi>Cyprei</hi> her Mother uncessantly ply the King, shewing him that the same hazard attended his Life and Crown, tho <hi>Mariamne</hi> was in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint; that such Birds were not to be kept in Cages, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104450:12"/> the delay of execution might hasten that of himself and estate, whereupon <hi>Herod</hi> giveth order to take away her life, which she suffered without change of colour, having an Aspect so sweet, that it might have drawn tears from the whole World; at this time <hi>Alexandra</hi> dyed in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mariamne</hi> of her chast wedlock left two Sons to <hi>Herod, viz. Alexander</hi> and <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> at that time young and uncapable of their own miseries; <hi>Herod</hi> to take them from the sense of this cruel Tragedy, and likewise to raise them in the degrees of good education, sends them to <hi>Rome</hi> to be bred in the Court of <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi> held at that time the Academy of Kings, and Prime School in the World; and having some time after a desire to salute the Emperour and see his Children, he made a Voyage to <hi>Italy,</hi> where he found them so excellently trained and wonderfully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished, that with the good leave of <hi>Caesar,</hi> he carried them back to <hi>Judea;</hi> these young Princes returning to <hi>Jerusalem</hi> with <hi>Herod,</hi> ravished all the people with admiration, they were of a gallant presence, quick-spirited, couragious in the exercise of Arms, and as lovely as the Father was odious, that they seemed to gain all hearts to approve their titles to the Crown. But now <hi>Pheroras</hi> Brother of <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Salome,</hi> who had dipped their fingers in the blood of the innocent Queen, entered into unspeakable apprehensions and affrightments, fearing that blood might sway one day over their heads, begins violently to calumniate them to the King, which he in the heat of the affection he bore them, gave no ear unto, but rather now seeing them draw near their maturity, sought to match them according to their quality; plotting for <hi>Alexander, Glaplyra</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Archelaus</hi> King of <hi>Capadocia;</hi> and caused <hi>Aristobulus, Mary</hi> the Daughter of his Sister <hi>Salome;</hi> whilst the two Brothers conversed together in all freedom and amity, <hi>Pheroras</hi> and <hi>Salome</hi> cease not to provoke them in all dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to speak on such subjects as they well knew could
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104450:13"/> draw some haughty or revengeful words from the young Princess; that whatsoever they said either thorough vanity or ready disposition to anger, or the liberty of secresie, was instantly related to <hi>Herod,</hi> and they caused by trusty instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments many rumors to pass into the ears of the King, the subtile <hi>Salome</hi> also holding still a power over her married Daughter, who was a simple creature; prevailed with her to tell all that her Husband and Brother-in-Law had spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the privacy of their mutual Conversation, all which their words, as on their part innocently spoken, so by her were as treacherously interpreted; <hi>Herod</hi> by their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al perswasions, after a long time filling his ears with mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious reports; begins to give footing to a grand suspition, and becometh cold in his Fatherly affection; which the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and malicious perceiving, hastned to strike the iron whilst it was hot; wishing the King seriously to take heed of his Sons, who speak bigg and high words, resolving all that had embrewed their hands in the blood of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, should not go unpunished, were it <hi>Herod</hi> himself; he gave credit to this false information with amazement at their Liberty; but what most incensed his rage was a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from one <hi>Antipater</hi> his Son, by <hi>Doris</hi> an <hi>Arcadian,</hi> whom he had sent to breed at <hi>Rome;</hi> importing that there he had discovered some strange plot against him, that he should take heed of his Brothers <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> who had practiced ill endeavours in every place, that they aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing less then to shorten his days, and depose him of his Empire. To this <hi>Herod</hi> gave intire credit, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly perplexing to see that having pacified all things abroad, such unquenchable fire should kindle in his house; he resolved to commit his Sons in security, but durst not attempt any thing upon them without <hi>Caesars</hi> consent; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had vexed his heart with a thousand anxieties, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved in his own person to go to <hi>Rome,</hi> carrying his Sons with him, that he might accuse them before <hi>Caesar,</hi> which he performed without showing the least appearance of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust
<pb facs="tcp:104450:13"/> towards his Children in all that long way between <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laestine</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and at length arriving in <hi>Rome, Caesar,</hi> it fell out was in <hi>Apuleia,</hi> whether he makes hast, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Aristobulus;</hi> the Emperour after <hi>Herods</hi> favourable reception entertaineth the two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (as a Father) with all demonstrations of love, which the subtile Father remarked, and whilst the Sons doubted nothing but their coming thither was their Fathers favour to laugh and sport away their time with their antient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintances, <hi>Herod</hi> espying his opportunity, demands a time of <hi>Augustus</hi> for an Audience, which he affirmed was upon an affair of great consequence which was granted him, and at the time appointed bringing with him the two Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, in the face of a brave assembly, breathing out a great sigh, he makes a most invective accusation against his two Sons, importing that he was a happy King thorough the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Emperour, but unhappy thorough the disqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets of his house; that natures gift of Children had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him miserable by a seditious progeny; that it were absurd to vex <hi>Caesars</hi> ears with such complaints, did not necessity inforce, and justice invite him to inform, that his two Sons, his unnatural Sons, after they had received from him all the favours could be expected from a King, and most indulgent Father, to breed them at the feet of <hi>Augustus,</hi> of whom he held his Crown, yet betraying that glorious edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation had at <hi>Caesars</hi> hands, and forgetting the nature and blood they had from him, they had attempted a crime fearful to be named, that they began to think he had lived too long in their eyes, that without waiting till natural death shall close up his eyes, they were endeavouring to pass through the Portal of Parricide, and had prepared ambushes for his life; that he would retain no right of judging in his own person, but demanded the Emperours Justice, which he begged might be given him, for his more safe repose in his own house in old age, and to be freed of the two Parricides, as the ungrateful tramplers of all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb facs="tcp:104450:14"/> and Humane Laws. This speech was uttered with so much vehemency, to the astonishment of the whole assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that the two young Princes fully replenished with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, began to cry at the hearing such tempestuous words; they endeavoured to speak, but the more they strove, the more were they interrupted, and their sobs choaked their words; <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> who was a judicious Gentile Prince, saw their aspect imported rather mishap then guilt, casting a gracious eye upon them, told them, that they might take courage, and be confident, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being overtroubled to answer at leisure; <hi>Herod</hi> was so moved in countenance, and so serious did he express him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that the whole hearers began to compassionate the young men, so moving was the Eloquence of the cruel Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But <hi>Alexander</hi> observing the favourable eyes of the multitude, expressing his sighs, in a most comely manner defendeth; directing this speech to <hi>Herod,</hi> saying, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conducted by his Warrant and Command before <hi>Caesar</hi> in the Temple of <hi>Clemence,</hi> it gave them occasion to say that his words were sharp but his proceedings sweet: that if calumny could have altered his nature to take resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on their lives over the belly of their innocence, he might have execute his wrath in <hi>Palestine:</hi> but God had brought it to pass otherways, that it was a strange thing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the most hard of crimes against persons of their repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and quality, with the alledging them parricides and all proofs pretermitted; if that be sufficient no more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency could abide in the world, but what calumny could not fix upon; that if their tears shed for their Mother, proceeding from the sincere resentment of nature were found criminal in the Court of their Father, where could they look for protection but from him; and begging that he would suppress his suspition already conceived, and that if he pleased to retain it, they would rather suffer death, not being so affectionatly fond of life as to will its preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the displeasure of him that gave it, this his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:104450:14"/> expressed with tears, amazed the whole audience, and as they stood in most humble demeanour waiting the issue, every one was inflam'd with a desire to justifie them. <hi>Caesar</hi> saw in the countenance of <hi>Herod</hi> the motion of compassion, as if he could have been content to have omitted the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation; for his cruelty was condemned by all, and telling the two Princes that they had done ill to displease their Father, that the crime was only a groundless pretension, ordaining <hi>Herod</hi> to raze it out of his remembrance, they mutually imbrace one another in the greatest appearance of joy expressible, wherein <hi>Antipater</hi> who had occasioned all this mischief acted his part: and now behold him return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them in the excess of all hypocritical congratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to <hi>Jerusalem:</hi> where scarcely one year was spent when calumny sets new snares to entrap the innocent Princes, and all indeavours are used by <hi>Pheroras</hi> the Brother of <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Salome</hi> his Sister, to stir up a more lasting division, by bewitching the Prince <hi>Alexander</hi> with a spirit of jealousie; insinuating to him that <hi>Herod</hi> his Father made too much of beautiful <hi>Graphina</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Archelaus,</hi> and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly laboured in this, that his spirit began to kindle with fury against his Father, still prying in <hi>Herods</hi> actions, who it is true, familiarly conversed with this Prince every day, being a person indued with many incomparable excellencies; although he could observe nothing in their conversations, saving the loving entertainments of a respective Father-in-Law of his Sons Wife, so well-deserving: yet the fire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased and so tormented the young Prince, that he could not withhold himself from discovering to <hi>Herod</hi> with sighs and tears of rage the jealousie and suspition he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, telling <hi>Pheroras</hi> to be its original, who Fathered all upon <hi>Salome. Herod</hi> found himself much troubled with this accident, and thinking it a thing below him to justifie himself to his own Son, he rather gave way in his heart to entertain a more inraged hatred against his Son; which the pernicious <hi>Antipater</hi> perceiving, being most gracious with
<pb facs="tcp:104450:15"/> his Father <hi>Herod,</hi> make use of this opportunity, beginning his battle more furiously than ever, and perceiving a great familiarity between <hi>Alexander</hi> and the three chief Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs belonging to <hi>Herod,</hi> informeth the King with all manner of serious perswasions, that the Conspiracies of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> so long in contriving, was now agreed upon; that the three most intimate Eunuches of his Chamber, had an hand in it, which he doubted not they would confess if they were put on rack; <hi>Herod</hi> who was a man that could have dispensed with any thing most cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, except attempts and practices against his state, is easily prevailed with: behold now the Eunuchs are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently put to the torture, whose bodies being corrupted with ease and delicacy; feeling the torment e're brought to speak what they knew and what they knew not, though nothing in the positive what <hi>Antipater</hi> pretended; who ceased not to bring in daily new accusations, which occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned much torture and racking. At this devilish and bloody Court thousand sottish and idle things were deposed that were to no effect; but the extream torture made some two or three declare, that <hi>Alexander</hi> had disgraced his Father at <hi>Rome,</hi> as inclining more with the <hi>Parthians</hi> than the <hi>Romans.</hi> That the two Brethren conspired to kill <hi>Herod</hi> by poison, then to go to <hi>Rome</hi> to demand the Kingdom, and willingly said yea to every question. Hereupon <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> is apprehended and put in safe custody, who much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at his own restraint, and the many tortures were daily committed, bitterly scoffing, sent the King one day word, that those torments and slaughters were needless, since he most freely confessed that whereas his Brother, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lame</hi> his Sister, and <hi>Ptolomey</hi> and <hi>Sapernias</hi> his Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, and himself, had conspired to kill all the world, that <hi>Herod</hi> alone might Reign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aristobulus</hi> used all means possible to procure his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers freedom, but so strange were the false apprehensions and jealousies of the King, and so assiduous were the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104450:15"/> informers, that nothing could prevail with <hi>Herod,</hi> until such time as <hi>Archelaus</hi> King of <hi>Capadocia</hi> his Father-in-law advertised of this disastor came to the Court of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod.</hi> This wise King understanding <hi>Herod</hi> to be a man who extreamly desired to justifie his most horrid and unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural actions, took great care not to offend him nor blame his credulity: but seemed compassionate to find him in such trouble, that his Children had done ill to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet him in that manner, that he could wish these misunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing were removed; and that he would rebuke his Daughter if she were blameable. <hi>Herod</hi> was exceedingly comforted to hear him speak in this manner, which was easily perceived by <hi>Archelaus,</hi> and that he had fallen in the right road of influencing <hi>Herod;</hi> by little and little at length he dissolved the Calumny, and <hi>Glaphyra</hi> assisting with prayers and tears obtained that the poor prisoners were released.</p>
            <p>Three years were not fully past, when behold the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Antipater</hi> living in the servitude of restless envy, sets new Engines up against the innocent Prince, well perceiving the life of <hi>Herod</hi> to be in the perpetual obscurity of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berless distrusts, and all readiness to act new cruelties upon groundless suspition and false jealousies; here discovereth that two Souldiers of <hi>Herods</hi> guard, lately disbanded for some slight offence, were contemptuously entertained in the house of <hi>Alexander,</hi> who not only to them, but to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther discontented persons ever became a Father and a sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply: thereby to make up a strong Poltis to promote and facilitate his conspiracies; that the putting these two Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to the torture, might be a means to secure the Kings life, and discover the most secret designs of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Aristobulus</hi> in the Government; for no doubt he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained them upon no other ground but to put his contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance in execution; these words prevailed with <hi>Herod,</hi> who without delay giveth order to accuse the two Souldiers as conspirators, and put them to torture for Confession.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104450:16"/>
            <p>The vehemency of the torment drove them to this false declaration, that at the solicitation of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stobulus,</hi> they had a plot upon the person of <hi>Herod</hi> to kill him as he was in hunting; also the Governour of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drina</hi> (which was one of the most strong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ortresses of that Kingdom) is accused as being willing to deliver it in the hands of those young Princes: which though he stoutly denyed, yet <hi>Herod</hi> most readily believeth, and without any further proof causeth to apprehend his two Sons, with a final purpose of heart to put them both to death, and within a very short space sendeth new Embassadors to <hi>Rome</hi> to purge himself of some slanders he was charged with, and accusing the two Princes in a most calumnious manner ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, intreateth of <hi>Caesar</hi> full liberty to dispose of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren according as Justice should require, which the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour rashly assented unto. <hi>Herod</hi> exceedingly rejoyced to have such dispatches, causeth to disgrace and defame the two young Princes with strong calumniations all <hi>Rome</hi> over, so that no man durst undertake their just defence, and to put the better face on his cruelties, and to colour his passion with Justice, he assembleth his counsel, to frame a formal Indictment against his two Sons, admitting all those whom he saw mischievously inclined to act in his bad pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. And sequestrating such as he feared might make any opposition, without suffering his Children to answer to their own justification, he entreth the Assembly himself full of Choler and bitterness; sometimes accusing, other while la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting within himself, at length in a rage he told the Assembly, he had not summoned them thither to judge, but to approve of his opinion, to the end Posterity might the more abhor Parricide, insisting as if the malefactors were already condemned by the sentence of <hi>Augustus,</hi> which in effect was nothing but a rash consent to a tryal, before the matter was put to the vote. One <hi>Saturnus</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> a man of great authority and judgment, disswadeth his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, with all his reason, holding out, that he himself was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104450:16"/> a Father, that he knew very well the price of Children, that <hi>Herod</hi> would repent him of his precipitation, and when his desires could not be obtain'd, then this murder would gnaw him to the heart. This discourse was seconded by some two or three, but to no purpose; it was opposed by one <hi>Volumnius,</hi> a rude and wicked man, who drew to his Faction all those who practiced to serve <hi>Herods</hi> passion, and so ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this cruel sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence that it was at length unjustly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded against the two innocent Sons of an inhumane and unnatural Parent. No sooner was this decree published, but it created a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neral grief amonst all; as unpossible to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press, as by many it was to undergo, who breathed out their last in fear and confusion. It is remarkable that one <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> an old Souldier of <hi>Herods,</hi> very passionate for the two Princes, went directly to the Palace, demanding to speak to the King himself, which was granted to him; where apart most boldly he admonished the King of the cruelty and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ustice of the Decree; telling him, that such proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings looked more like to the actions of such as had lost their wits, than of a prudent Prince; that it was an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable loss to the people to see the true Heirs of the Crown put to death, to advance a Viper who one day would sting him to the death. <hi>Herod</hi> seemed at first to give ear to this admonition, but having made inquiry after who it was had taken exception at this judgment, inraged thereat he cast <hi>Triphon</hi> in prison, and laying hold upon all the rest he condemneth them all to death. The two Princes his Sons he sends to <hi>Sebaste,</hi> commanding the most cruel of his guards to strangle them in prison, which was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly put in execution, breathing out their royal souls un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hands of the hangman, the unfortunate <hi>Graphina</hi> now meeteth with the hard news of her husbands death, and her own Widowhood, which cast her in a trance, and so as mute as any Statue; but at length in some time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting her self, she gave <hi>Herod</hi> a grievous sigh, saying, wo's me! who would have thought that <hi>Herod</hi> would
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104450:17"/> have committed this cruelty, tell him the sacrifice of his fury is not quite finished; behold here one part of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim is still alive, in whose heart <hi>Alexanders</hi> memory shall still dwell, who had no other for his executioner but him whom nature had ordained for a Father, wo's me, that I was call'd to receive the last groans of thy pensive soul, to embosom thy final words, and incase them in my heart! and turning aside to two little Children which she had with <hi>Alexander,</hi> poor Orphans, said she, what a Father have they nefariously snatched away from you? alas! you are too soon taught the trade of misery. Thus disconsolately afflicting her spirit, being no longer able to bear the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of her grief, she breathed her last, leaving her two Sons to the protection of the gods, whom <hi>Herod</hi> took care to keep, rather on design to establish himself than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and fearing their name might serve for pretext to some revolt. But <hi>Herod</hi> who now proposed peace and quiet to himself in his Government, being afraid of nothing so much as that his Crown might have been taken from him, who for keeping it on his head had committed so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny murders, and practiced so much cruelty, is ever disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, meeting constantly with such inward checks, from the guilt of his wicked actions, that he is continually tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with tortering confusions and fears: amongst which that of Jesus Christ's coming into the world had greatest place; there having come at this time three Kings from some far Countrey, miraculously guided to <hi>Jerusalem</hi> by a Star, and making it their great errand of discovering him who was born King of the Jews, revealing the wonderful guide had lead them thither, the arrival of those great persons in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the strange design they came for, occasioned great amazement and wonder over all <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastine,</hi> but in <hi>Herod</hi> great fear and terror: beginning now to look upon the Kingdom of <hi>Judea</hi> as altogether rent out of his hands by some divine right and irresistable power, against which all his cunning and subtilty would be to small
<pb facs="tcp:104450:17"/> purpose: amidst these confusions he recollecteth himself, resolving to make all search to find out the revelation of this mysterious accident, so that having consulted with the chief Priests and Scribes, the Learned amongst the Jewish Nation, they discover to him an antient Prophecy, careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept &amp; faithfully waited on for its accomplishment by all that people, foretelling that in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Judea</hi> should be born one who should govern and rule over all <hi>Israel;</hi> this antient Prophesie seemed now to be fulfilled, in that these great men were so wonderfully guided to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> where they hoped to find that promised King: and it so confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Herod</hi> with fears, that now he resolves to assay his cunning cruelty; and having had private conference with the Wise men, endeavouring to learn what had befallen them, and the errand they so carefully went about, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with their design in all his outward behaviour, he favourably dismisseth them, having given them commssion to make diligent search for the Child, and to return to him with the accompt thereof, that he also might perform holy service and worship to this adorable King, of long time fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, and now at length most wonderfully come into the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> now acting his master piece of Hypocrisie, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered well that he could imploy none who would with more prudence and less neglect use all diligence in finding out this promised King: not doubting but the allurements of these presents he had formerly given them, would ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidge them to comply with his desires, fully purposeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter discovery of this harmless Infant, instead of adoration cruelly to imbrue his hands in the blood of the Saviour of the world, &amp; finding himself cock-sure, having so solidly laid the way in cutting off this new-born King of the Jews, behold the Wisemen having performed all the rites necessary, and presented the Babe with inestimable offerings of Gold, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincence and Myrrh; return homeward another way, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out visiting <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Joseph</hi> the supposed Father of <hi>Jesus,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104450:18"/> and <hi>Mary</hi> his betrothed Wife, flee to <hi>Egypt,</hi> for preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Child from <hi>Herods</hi> intended cruelty. The Wise men and <hi>Joseph</hi> having both had revelations from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for this purpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>In great impatience did <hi>Herod</hi> wait the Wise mens return to him, but at length out of all hopes, easily perceived him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self mocked, and his projects disappointed, that there was nothing more apparent then his dethronement, if this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised King should live, he issueth forth an Edict, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to kill all the Children about <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem</hi> and in <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee</hi> that were under two years old, according to the time he had diligently inquired of the Wise-men, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was most barbarously executed, even to the cutting off of fourteen thousand Innocents, a Massacre not paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in any History; but what was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Herod</hi> would not have committed, rather than quit his authority, even in his old age, to attempt upon the Son of God, whom he understood came to possess his earthly Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> after all his horrid cruelties seeks to sit on his Throne in peace, where the detestable <hi>Antipater</hi> thought he had already one foot in, seeing the two righteous Heirs of the Crown removed quite away through his practices, which were so recent in the minds of all the people, that they hated him like a Tyger, and the Souldiers who saw him embrewed in the blood of his Brothers, could in no sort relish him; this <hi>Antipater</hi> well enough perceived, and therefore thought fit to withdraw himself, thereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline envy; in his departure he avoided the seeking the love of his Father, for fear he should minister matter of suspition, but he caused Letters closely to be written from <hi>Rome</hi> to his Father, by friends whom he had wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that purpose, which imported that it was necessary <hi>Antipater</hi> should be sent to <hi>Rome</hi> to break the enterprises the <hi>Arabians</hi> had against the state of <hi>Judea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having received these Letters, he quickly dispat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched his Son <hi>Antipater</hi> with a good train, and rich pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104450:18"/> but what was above all, in a costly and sumptuous little Box, he delivered unto him his Will and Testament, wherein he declares him King of <hi>Judea</hi> after his death, a short time after <hi>Antipater</hi> was gone from <hi>Jerusalem</hi> it fell out that the mischievous <hi>Pheroras,</hi> who had acted to his power, in this lamentable Tragedy, is found dead, poyson<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as was supposed by the maid-servant, whom he had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and <hi>Herod</hi> is prayed to come to the house of his Brother to take examination of the fact, where unexpected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he learned that <hi>Antipater</hi> had conspired the death of <hi>Herod,</hi> which was to be committed by <hi>Pheroras,</hi> giving his Brother the King a dose of poyson, <hi>Antipater</hi> had left with him at his going to <hi>Rome,</hi> on purpose to dispatch <hi>Herod</hi> that he might speedily return to <hi>Palaestine</hi> with a Crown on his head; at the same time <hi>Bathillus,</hi> set at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty by <hi>Antipaters</hi> procurement, was taken coming from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Indus</hi> to advise <hi>Pheroras</hi> to hasten the business, and bringing with him a new poison if the first was not of force. In the mean time <hi>Antipater</hi> ceaseth not writing to his Father, acquainting him with the state of all affairs, and that in short time he hoped so to accomodate these matters he was about, that his return would be very quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into <hi>Judea. Herod</hi> laying hold on these expressions, taketh occasion to write this insuing Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>MY Son, the frailty through my Age and debility of my Body, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ily instructeth me that I am mortal; one thing comforteth me, that having made choice of your person to succeed in my state, I should behold the decreepid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of my age flourish again in your youth, and as it were bury my death in your life, since I shall live in one part of my self to me most precious, I wish ye were presently with me, not so much for the assistance I expect from your counsel, as the prejudice your absence may impose upon my Fortune, fail not with good leave of <hi>Caesar</hi> to make hast hither, delay nothing to advance our affairs.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104450:19"/>
            <p>This bait was too tempting to defend him from the hook: upon this Letter he would as it were fly to <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> he dispatcheth his affairs, takes leave of <hi>Augustus,</hi> and hastily posteth to obey his Fathers commands. In the way passing through <hi>Silicia</hi> he learned that his mother was in some disfavour, without hearing any thing of <hi>Pheroras,</hi> this much amazed him, so that he purposed to retire back, but one of his counsellors, perhaps wrought upon by <hi>Herod,</hi> shewed him, that if nothing was plotted against him, he ought not to fear, and if any calumny were forged, he ought rather to hasten to strangle it, otherways his absence would thrust him into a further suspition. This counsel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing, he took way to <hi>Judea,</hi> and arrived in the Port of <hi>Sebaste,</hi> he goeth directly from thence to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and hastneth to the Palace magnificently attired, and well atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the guard suffered him to enter, commanding all those who accompanied him to withdraw in the Kings name, he was much astonished at this, to see himself taken like a Bird in the snare. Notwithstanding, he entred the Hall, where his Father expected him, accompanied with <hi>Quintilius Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> newly sent from <hi>Rome</hi> as Governour of <hi>Syria,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made an humble obeysance as it is customary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching to kiss his Fathers hands; at that time began the Lyon to roar, for <hi>Herod</hi> retiring back, cried out, avaunt thou murtherer of Brothers and Father, the kiss of a Father was not instituted for thee, behold <hi>Quintilius</hi> thy Judge, advise with thy self what thou art to morrow to answer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on crimes whereof thou art accused.</p>
            <p>These words did <hi>Herod</hi> utter with such an angry coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, that the guilty <hi>Antipater</hi> was struck therewith as with a most violent thunder-bolt, bearing terror in the image of the crime in his face, he departeth to the chamber ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for him, where he spent the whole night in great afflictions of mind, convicting himself of the great facility there is in committing, over what there is in excusing a crime.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104450:19"/>
            <p>The next day he is sent for by the Council, where he found the King his Father with <hi>Quintilius Varro</hi> already placed, and many more of the Counsellors; whilst each are repairing to their accustomed seats in the Councel, some one or other who favoured <hi>Antipater,</hi> whispereth him in the ear, that lately there were Letters intercepted written by his Mother, which signified that all was discovered, and that he should carefully beware, and not put himself into the hands of his Father, if he desired to avoid cruel tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and death. This struck him to the very heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning now to cast off all hopes of escaping in this tryal, if he stood out to reasoning, and therefore rushing forwards, he throws himself upon his face, in the most submissive man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to his Father, makes shew to speak and beg his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Herod</hi> incensed with fury and revenge, not giving him leave to speak, cryeth out, impious villain, contriver of the most wicked fratricide, what canst thou say? hath God preserved thee to be the last scourge of my old age? thou knowest I have extracted thee out of the dregs, to place thee over thy Brothers; above and beyond all hope I have given thee my mony, my revenues, my authority, my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, my secrets, my heart, and Crown into thy hands; and thou canst not stay a little till thy Fathers eyes are closed up by natural death to enjoy it. Surely it was thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy purpose aim'd, when with such heat and cunning thou didst pursue the death of thy Brothers, for thy advice and information inforc'd me to all I did, so that I am afraid thou hast stained me with their blood, and now thy crime makes their innocency appear. <hi>Herod</hi> was not able to speak more, and it was observed that tears dropt from his eyes, for his cruel heart was troubled when the memory of <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amne</hi> and his unfortunate Children came into his mind, which so opprest him, that he was inforced to intreat <hi>Damasenas</hi> who was his Counsellor, to prosecute the rest.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104450:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Antipater</hi> no sooner saw his Father retire, but preventing <hi>Damasenus</hi> applying himself to <hi>Quintilius Varro,</hi> spoke most boldly in his own defence, telling, that he was much wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in giving credit to slaves and silly women to his preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, that the Letters he had from <hi>Caesar</hi> could give a sufficient testimony of his demeanour, and of the satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction he had given at <hi>Rome</hi> on the behalf of <hi>Herod,</hi> in whose affairs he had laboured in all assiduity and care; that he never had fail'd in duty towards his Father; and that it were a passage of extream folly, to put himself into an uncertain hazard for a Crown, which already he had as it were in his hands, and that without any further, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course he offer'd himself to be us'd like a Slave, and to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo any torture for proof of his innocence. This he spoke with such passion, that many of those present be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be moved. But <hi>Damasenus</hi> taking him up, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting the witnesses, after several interrogations, whilst <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater</hi> is invoking the Heavens for some extraordinary delivery. Behold (saith he) what a brutish stupidity it is, to conspire against your Father, having as yet the Blood of your Brothers before your eyes, and all the assurances of the Scepter in your hands? and why would you become a Parricide to hasten for your self that Crown which was so fully fasten'd upon you in the authentick Testament of your Father? Why did you thirst so earnestly after the Blood of the King, whose life is so dear to all honest men; and who to you hath been indulgent above his other Children, or your own merit? This your ingratitude is able to make Heaven blush, and the Earth tremble under your feet; an ingratitude that all the Elements should conspire to punish it, so that you need not expect any extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary favour from Heaven to relieve you; but if you have any good reasons, boldly make them known, for the King your Father desireth nothing more than your justification. <hi>Antipater</hi> could give no other answer then what he had said formerly, he stood confounded like a lost man. <hi>Varro</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104450:20"/> having now drawn the Trial to a point, causeth to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister some of the poison to an Offendor already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, who instantly died. And all the Assembly arose, with manifest declarations of <hi>Antipaters</hi> guilt. There was at that time only one <hi>Antiphalus</hi> whom <hi>Antipater</hi> blamed, saying, that he had brought the poison, and had been the sole wicked person who occasion'd all his unhappiness. It was admired of many, that <hi>Herod</hi> did not order the sentence of death to be put instantly in execution; but he resolved to inform <hi>Caesar</hi> of all that had passed, and in the mean time <hi>Antipater</hi> is straitly imprisoned, expecting hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a miserable Victim the stroak of death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> was now about seventy years of age, and had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready felt through imbecility of body, the approach of his last hour, which was hard for him to digest, he above all men best loving this present life, who though he had been therein the most unhappy, yet would freely have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken his part of the next world, to enjoy this. Towards the end of his days he grew so harsh and unpleasant, so cholerick and furious, that his maenial Servants had much ado to attend him. They handled him in his own Palace as an old Lyon, chain'd with the fetters of an incurable malady, he perswaded himself that he was hated of all the world, upon the reason he had given too great occasion thereof, and the people began to forget their duty, with an impatience that could no longer indure him, so that when his sickness and distemper began to be noised abroad, the Principal Doctors of the Jewish Nation, who had all the youth of <hi>Judea</hi> at command, having of a long time been grieved at the cruelty of <hi>Herod,</hi> in that he for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of his own estate, and to idolize the fortunes of <hi>Caesar;</hi> had at the reparation of the Temple of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> set upon the principal Gate, the Roman Eagles all glistering in gold: since by their Law they were forbidden the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges either of men or beasts, or any other figures in their Temples, they most devoutly abhorred them: and trusting
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104450:21"/> that the sickness of <hi>Herod</hi> afforded them the conveniency of revenge, <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Mathias</hi> who were the chief, exhort the most valiant of the young men to take the quarrel of their God in hand, according to the spirit of their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, to beat down those most horrid abominations which were fixed upon the most holy Temple; that <hi>Herod</hi> had enough to do to wrestle with his own pain, and that to dye in such a glorious act, was to be buried in the midst of glory and triumph. There needed not great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the zealous youths for this enterprize, for in less th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n half a day there, gathered together a great troop of most valiant young men, armed with axes and hatchets, who climbed to the top of the Temple, and hewed to pieces the Roman Eagles in sight of all the beholders. <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Mathias</hi> being present serving for trumpets in this exploit. The noise of this in short time reacheth the Palace, and the Captain of the Guard came thither with the most resolute of his Souldiers, he feared some further Plot, and that this defacing the Eagles might prove a preamble of a greater se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but at first as he began to charge, the people retired, and in pursuit took forty of the young men. <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Mathias</hi> deeming it an unworthy and unbecoming thing to fly, were carried along with them, and presented to <hi>Herod,</hi> who demanded from whence this boldness proceeded; they very freely answered, that the design was fully agreed upon amongst themselves, and if it were to do again, they would be in readiness to put it in execution, in regard they were more bound to the observance of <hi>Moses</hi> Law, then any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand coming from <hi>Herod.</hi> This their resolute answer ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the King, and bred in him fears of greater commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which caused them to be carried secretly to <hi>Jericho,</hi> whether himself, though infirm, was carried in a very short time, and assembling some few, spoke to them in a very fair manner, narrating to them the good offices he had done to the whole Nation, that he had repaired the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and inriched it with many comely ornaments of great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104450:21"/> cost, and that he had done in few years more then the <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modian</hi> Kings could perform in many, and instead of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and recompence of his piety at noon-day, they had hewn down with inconsiderate boldness, a most beseeming gift he had raised on the Temple, for which he required a reason. The Jews catching him in this pleasant humor, wanting his accustomed fury, and fearing any further to incense him, declined the danger, and put him upon their companions, leaving them to the mercy of the King, who at that time took the Priesthood from <hi>Mathias,</hi> and caused him with another who was accounted a great author of the sedition, and their companions to be burned alive that very night. At which time an Eclipse of the Moon was seen, which rendered this spectacle much more dreadful. And notwithstanding the maladies of his body increased, which did wast it every day with longing torments, when at this time he should have minded eternity, it is now his great study how to commit moe cruelties and horrid slaughters, which he executed almost to the rooting out of the Jewish Nation. This very time of his sickness, this most despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate wretch published an Edict, calling together the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal of the Jews to meet him at <hi>Jericho</hi> out of every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, whom he instantly shut up in close prison without giving any reason why, and thereafter sending <hi>Salome</hi> his Sister and her <hi>Alexandras</hi> whom he knew both to be as cruel as himself, to them he committed the execution of his most bloody Will.</p>
            <p>Telling them, that it troubled him not to dye and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tribute which all Kings must pay, but it afflicted him that his death would not be lamented if they assisted not, he wished them therefore to take notice that he gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red under sure custody all the nobility of <hi>Judea,</hi> whom he now put over in their hands, to the end that so soon as his eyes were closed, they should instantly be all put to the sword. That they should not divulge his death till the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of these people were known to their friends, hereby
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104450:22"/> he thought to fill all <hi>Palaestine</hi> with tears, and his soul would leave his body with more contentment, beseeching his Sister by all she esteemed most glorious and most sacred in the world, that she would omit nothing of this his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, and rested not content until she confirmed her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise with a solemn oath, and so returned unto <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> where he received Letters from <hi>Rome</hi> written by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Caesar,</hi> which certified him that one <hi>Acme</hi> a Jews Lady of <hi>Livia</hi>'s train, had been condemned for holding sinister intelligence with <hi>Antipater,</hi> and for that cause was punished with death, but for his Son he wholly left him to his own disposal, this news refreshed <hi>Herod</hi> exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and he sucked this ground of vengeance upon his Son with such a marvellous sweetness, that even in that joy he took some fits which gave occasion to all the beholders to expect nothing else but present death, and one of them gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a terrible out-cry, put all the Palace in an uproar. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater</hi> in the Prison cometh to hear this tumult, supposing <hi>Herod</hi> to be at his last breathing, his feet itched in his fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, raising himself in hopes still to enjoy the Crown, if death should take away the King before the sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him were executed, without either fear or dispair of success, intreateth his keeper for his liberty, not failing to promise him vast sums of money, and the highest of Court-preferments: But the Jaylor who better understood how matters went at the Palace, and fearing that the ravenous claws of <hi>Herod</hi> might be strong enough to tear him in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, without having regard of the promised rewards, went directly to the King, and there relateth to him the ways and means <hi>Antipater</hi> had used to get out of Prison, and take possession of the Kingdom: which <hi>Herod</hi> no sooner heard, but with as high a voice as his sickness could permit him, he cried out, Heavens! will the parricide murder me in my bed? there is life enough left me yet to take away his, and calling to him two of his Guards, he gave them immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately orders to go to the prison and kill his Son, ordering
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104450:22"/> him to be buried in an old Castle without any funeral so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, which was accordingly done, and in few days thereafter <hi>Herod</hi> declareth <hi>Archelaus</hi> his successor to the Kingdom. There was not any humane remedy left unsaid for preservation of life in this cursed wretch, but all to no purpose; for albeit age, the accomplisher of all natural infirmities, had reduced him to great decay of body, yet were his spirits fresh and lively, so that he might have lived some years longer, but the Heavens, who could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out indignation behold this miscreant Tyger depart this life, without pouring upon him most tormenting tokens of divine displeasure at his detestable cruelty and blood-shed, assault him with a furious troop of incurable pains, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he is tormented with a burning heat in his bowels, other times afflicted with a dog-like hunger, continually crying for meat, eating and yet never satiat, sometimes his feet swelled with painful and phlegmatick humors, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times outragious and intolerable cholicks racked him; some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time an Asthma hindered his breathing, othertimes cramps and convulsions affect his whole joints, and oftentimes all these act their parts forcibly at once: till at length this wretched Caitif, he who shed the blood of the admirable <hi>Mariamne</hi> of comely <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> of <hi>Joseph</hi> and of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>Aristobulus:</hi> briefly, he who imbrued his hands in the blood of all the Nobility of <hi>Judea,</hi> and wallowed in the massacre of fourteen thousand innocent Children, in purpose to catch in this cruelty the Saviour of Man-kind, is further assaulted with a vehement flux, and all the parts of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy filled over with lice and vermine, yieldeth over his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed soul in rage and despair, the seventieth year of his age, and thirty seventh of his reign. He was a Prince who all his life made himself master of his Laws, and slave of his Passion; and notwithstanding of all his honour and success, may be reputed amongst the most miserable, having passed his days for the most part in cankering apprehensions, thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny affairs, fearful distrusts, dreadful fears, barbarous cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104450:23"/> inhumane blood-sheds, and such like forerunners of Hell, leaving after him a hateful name, and a short and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Posterity.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Printed and are to be Sold by <hi>Enoch Wyer,</hi> at the <hi>White Hart</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard.</head>
            <list>
               <head>In Folio.</head>
               <item>CLARKS General Martyrology, 1677. price 1 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baylii Opera Chronolog. &amp; Hist. Amsterdam,</hi> 1663. price 8 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Twiffe de scientia Medica</hi> 1639. 7 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Strodes</hi> Doctrine of Combination of Qualities, pr. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 1677.</item>
               <item>A Letter to a Gentleman in answer to a Discourse concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Period of Human Life, 1677. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Apollonius Magnus Gregorianus &amp; Cardanus promotus a</hi> Tho. Baker, <hi>now in the Press.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Octavo <hi>and</hi> Twelves.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eustathii Ethica</hi> 8. 1677. price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Discourse concerning the Period of Human Life, whether mutable or immutable: By the Author of the Duty of Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Second Edition, 1677. 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Description of the Islands of <hi>Foeroe</hi> in the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks</hi> Dominions, illustrated with Maps, N. 1677. price 2<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Martials</hi> Epigrams for the use of <hi>Westm.</hi> School, 12. 1677. price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Galei Idea Theologiae,</hi> 12. 1676. price 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Galei Philosophica Generalis,</hi> 8. 1677. price 9 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lightfoots <hi>Horae Hebraicae &amp; Talmudicae, in Corinthios,</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, a <hi>Paris</hi> 1677, price 4 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>